[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is a sutta called the Uposatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's about the observance day.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, at that time, it being the Uposatha day, Visakha went to the Blessed One in the middle of the day, and on arrival, having bowed down to Him, sat to one side.
[SPEAKER_01]: As she was sitting there, the Blessed One said to her, Well, now, Visakha, why are you coming in the middle of the day?
[SPEAKER_01]: Today, I'm observing the uposita.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha says, Visakha, there are these three upositas.
[SPEAKER_01]: The uposita of the cow herd, the one who watches the other people's cows.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shepherd.
[SPEAKER_01]: The shepherd.
[SPEAKER_01]: The uposita of the giants and the uposita of the noble ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the... what is the uposita of the cow herd?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as when a cow herd
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's call it the shepherd.
[SPEAKER_01]: Returns the sheep to their owners in the evening.
[SPEAKER_01]: He reflects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today the sheep wandered to that spot and this, drank at this spot and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tomorrow they will wander to that spot and this, will drink at this spot and that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way, there is the case where a certain person, observing the uposata, reflects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today I ate this sort of food and that sort of food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Tomorrow, I will eat that sort of food and this sort of food.
[SPEAKER_01]: He spends the day with an awareness imbued with that covetousness, with that greed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such is the poster of the shepherd, Visākha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, he's thinking about centrality, what he had, what he will have, how he will have it, working for it, planning for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what he's observing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the observance of his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those values are values that his mind is observing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's the
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the type of uposatha.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the type of observance.
[SPEAKER_00]: What did I have?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where did I have it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How I had it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did I have more of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where did I get more of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: More of the same, new stuff, sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the sheep, drink here, eat there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the way normal people, well, the majority of people...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like whatever the uninstructed mind would do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what the values are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Protecting the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting more pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Avoiding pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, like thinking about the past pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I get more of the same?
[SPEAKER_00]: More of the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that does require, you know, people, like, take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't necessarily develop self-awareness, but if they would become self-aware, they would realize that that requires planning, and observing, and contemplating, and deciding, and actually it involves quite a lot of work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is a type of observance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's that anticipation, that practice of anticipating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what's like a driving force.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that anticipation, the ride.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's what gives you the energy and inspiration to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to immediately reflect on the results that you experienced so many times before, like results of
[SPEAKER_00]: Satisfa... of allowing your senses to feed carelessly where they want to, you realize, well, actually, that's... it's not that much.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that great.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've done it before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's approaching the idea of result through the mind of anticipation, then it's always like infinite pleasure promise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although you know it's not, you know it's gonna last for a bit, you experience it many times, but you forget, or you don't put the result first, you put your anticipation first, and then you can't resist the ride.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although you know it's going to have a very limited result.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your anticipation becomes the driving force.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the delight in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the gratification of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not getting what you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's allowing delight to be first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how you gratify your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Joy and zeal and delight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you think, unless now, well, you have to be able to reflect on this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, this is what I'm cultivating.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anticipation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anticipation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if I get that and more of what I anticipated, what I'm cultivating the whole time is anticipation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anticipation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what I will have in the future, for sure, is anticipation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if I get the content of what I'm anticipating, that anticipation, that mind of anticipation, overrides everything that I would get
[SPEAKER_01]: Particularly, specifically, whatever food, whatever tangible experience, my mind will be... That is exactly...
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha talks about understanding the gratification of sensuality, it's that, chanda, the delight, the zeal, the anticipation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the contact with the agreeable object.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already gratifying your sensuality by allowing the anticipation to be first, by accepting it, by welcoming it, by delighting it further.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the inspiration, the uplifting, the joy towards... that's already your gratification of centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, everything else that follows through the framework of anticipation, is just proliferation of that gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's never-ending, because the framework of anticipation, yeah, can last infinitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have to keep it going.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just keep finding new stuff here and there, to rekindle the anticipation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the gratification is that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Anticipation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Khandhā means zeal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can mean, like, all of these, you know, it can mean good zeal, but it can mean bad zeal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you're very inspired, anticipating, full of energy, full of, like, effort, and ready to do the work to get sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not, later on, touching the result of the sensual pleasure that's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What people usually regard as satisfaction of my desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your satisfaction began
[SPEAKER_00]: When you jumped onto that kind of pressure, that sort of effortless sort of ride of anticipation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why sensuality is intoxicating, because it masks all the effort you are actually doing, but you are unaware of it, because it feels effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is no anticipation towards the sense pleasure, even like, you know, not so
[SPEAKER_00]: Difficult tasks feel like depressing, feel heavy, feel pointless, feel hard to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all you need to do is put that, like, cherry on the top as waiting for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The carrots.
[SPEAKER_00]: The carrots, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it just becomes absolutely effortless, while in reality, you do much more as a result of that anticipation, nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why in some suttas, you know, the Buddha talked about danger of gratification, danger of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: He talked about it in different contexts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, always arriving at the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in some suttas, he said,
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger of sensuality is having to work fields, sweat, endure the heat to earn the money, to get married, to have family, to protect, to work for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, yeah, that's all kind of what your anticipation is based on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're doing all these things, hard work, unnecessary work, because it's all kind of bonded together with this idea of
[SPEAKER_00]: The great result that is only great because you put anticipation first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's already your gratification of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't put the anticipation first, you allow the reflection to recognize everything you do on account of sensuality, and then, at the same time, you see the end result of that sensuality, that that carrot, and then you realize, oh, this is not a good deal.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's easy to forget if you put the anticipation first and the carrot second, and the the sense pleasure second, and then everything else becomes invisible,
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's just this effortless inspired zeal that you're just flying weightless on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why sensuality is intoxicating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it just feels you're not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like done to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's enjoyable because it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in reality, it's actually completely the opposite of the effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the effort before, in the middle, and after, they will follow.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a strain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Major strain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a perpetual strain that is not felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the perversion of the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perversion of the order, in this case, is putting the anticipation first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, allowing that to sort of become the framework for everything else you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it masks the weight of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the trick of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, don't put the anticipation first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't act out of it first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discern the wider background while you're anticipating.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, things will just fall into place.
[SPEAKER_00]: The lack of satisfaction, the disgust, the peril, the actual ugliness of it, and then your anticipation will just fizzle out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when gratification has been understood and abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have zeal anymore on account of that direction of sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you have zeal towards renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a good chanda, good zeal, good desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see, the danger of anticipation, as I was saying, that your whole, you know, your whole mind is just driven by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you can't stop yourself eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can see the places it's taking you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The states of mind that it's dragging you through, but you can't stop having that craving and cultivating that craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't stop having it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can stop cultivating it by not putting it first, by enduring it, and then broadening the picture, as I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you will stop having it, eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you stop feeding it, it will die out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you also can see the future dangers, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine if I keep doing this for 50 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, of course, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I keep doing this for 50 years,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's craving, fantasizing, going after the essential pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually, I'll get old and everything will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, what happens is, the longer you do it, the stronger the craving becomes, the weaker you become.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the poster of the Giants?
[SPEAKER_01]: There are the contemplatives called the Giants, the Gantas.
[SPEAKER_01]: They get their disciples to undertake the following practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say, here, my good man,
[SPEAKER_01]: Lay down your weapons with regard to beings who live more than a hundred leagues to the east, to the west, to the north, to the south.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, they get their disciple to undertake kindness and compassion to some beings, not to others.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's different to kind of James, as I know, as you know, they want to protect all beings, but anyway...
[SPEAKER_01]: On the uposita or and on the uposita day, they get their disciple to undertake the following practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say, here, my good man, having taken off all your clothing, say this, I am nothing to anyone, anywhere, and nobody is anything to me, anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's not, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The foremost, one of the foremost views of an outsider.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am nothing towards anyone, nothing, no one's mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am not anybody's.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they get that person to say that, to declare that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, in spite of that, his parents know him, know of him, that this is our child.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he knows them, that these are my parents.
[SPEAKER_01]: His wives and children know him, that this is our husband and father.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he knows them, that these are my wives and children.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so on with his workers.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, he he's not practicing what he's declaring.
[SPEAKER_00]: He hasn't been practicing and he has no plans of doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's just declaring it, because he's in the presence of a Samana Brahman, that...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's just going along with it for whatever benefit he believes he's going to get from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some special mantra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's no different at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some special practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, at that time, when he should be persuaded to undertake truthfulness, he's persuaded to undertake falsehood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end of the night, he resumes the consumption of his belongings.
[SPEAKER_01]: He takes back his clothing and things and he's given up and nothing's his.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even though they aren't given back to him, and he gave them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: This counts as stealing, it says, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I tell you, such is the apostle of the giants, when this apostle of the giants is undertaken.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he gave the example of the giants, because obviously it was probably prominent at the time, but you could see the principle of that is basically taking on the practice superficially.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think that's sort of what he describes the medals pretty much
[SPEAKER_00]: Most of the temples today, where people go and take the precepts, because they offer the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they go through the motion of chanting the precepts, declaring the precepts, knowing, even beforehand, that the moment they leave the monastery, precepts won't apply to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: They'll carry on drinking or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, it's done by both.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the monks are encouraging, exactly like giant scum good men, take the precepts, it's good for you, you make merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they do so, both, while knowing it's just gonna be for the duration of the chant, and maybe till the end of the day,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they go back to their own life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Normally, nothing has changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not really an opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's a type of opposite, as you can see, like opposed on the surface, which is worse, because it's even more dishonest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because many people do genuinely believe, certainly traditional Buddhists, that by simply by taking the precepts, without the intention of keeping them, they are accruing merit somehow, somewhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, look, I am doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I'm cleaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a form of cleansing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, take your clothes, put these clothes, wash your hair, you know, bow to the four directions, whatever giant we're doing or other brahmins.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just going through the motions that obviously are kind of held together with the belief of
[SPEAKER_00]: I went to church on a Sunday, said my prayers, cleared the week.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the uposta of the noble ones?
[SPEAKER_01]: It is the cleansing of the defiled mind through the proper technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: And how is the defiled mind cleansed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the proper technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is the case where a disciple of the Noble Ones, a noble disciple, recollects the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Indeed, the Blessed One is worthy, rightly, self-awakened, consummate in knowledge and conduct, well-gone, an expert with regard to the world,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, faith in the teaching, in the teacher, the teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: As he is recollecting like this, his mind is calmed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Joy arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: The defilements of his mind are abandoned, just as when the head is cleansed through proper technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it gives like through soap and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I said, exactly what people believed.
[SPEAKER_00]: By washing your your hands with the soap, with this water, in that direction, you're cleansing your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But Buddha says, yes, through a technique of recollecting the Buddha, the dhamma, the saṅgha, on the basis of your right view, recollecting the quality of enlightenment, the path, the knowledge, you are cleansing your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: By bringing up and thinking about those contexts, those themes,
[SPEAKER_00]: of enlightenment, awakening, freedom from suffering, on the basis of your right views, on the basis of seeing what your mind actually is, then, yes, that results in the actual purification, like what people believe of washing it, you know, the method and the motions of how you wash it and how you prostrate, like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how people believe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is what actually cleans your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're bowing down like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cleans the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The recollection of the Buddha on the basis of your right view... That cleans your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the right themes, the right contemplations clean your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we said so many times, as the Buddha said in many suttas, what you often think and ponder about, that becomes the direction of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an inclination, it slopes, it goes that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you often think and ponder about liberation, suffering, the peril of sensuality, the mind will turn away from those things that are contradictory to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that needs to be, like, yeah, observed regularly, sustained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thought about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thought about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pondered on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rekindle your zeal towards that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inspiration towards thinking those themes that kind of initially go against your experience and certainly against the experience of a central household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you think about them long enough, they will... the values behind those themes, those contexts, will take place, will take root,
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll start to grow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... you don't really hear about that often.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just think about the Buddha and his qualities.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of... Well, because, yeah, people... Well, first of all, as with many other suttas, people ignore the fact that you need to be a Sotāpanna first for that to apply to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having ignored that fact, then it becomes easy to... Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: We already do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's taken for granted that everybody already does that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize, well, actually, follow further in the same sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are the results that should follow, if you do that rightly, on the basis of the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do you have the results to follow?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is your mind inspired because you think you are saved by the Lord Buddha?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is your mind inspired because it's incapable of lust and aversion towards very unfavorable circumstances?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the confidence towards, I cannot be defiled internally, confidence comes on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that your zeal, your inspiration, or because the Lord Buddha is always looking over you and everything will work out?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's different.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or maybe not specifically such a kind of personified idea of the Lord Buddha, but do you hold the belief that everything will work out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything will be fine for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is that belief rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it a factual recognition of your right view, sotāpati, so you know you are beyond the states of peril and so on?
[SPEAKER_00]: Factual recognition of the purified states of mind that you know for fact, like you see them, pure and impure, you avoid impure, you cultivate the pure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it just wishful thinking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything will work out.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the basis of what?
[SPEAKER_00]: You have such observance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can start imagining the Buddha, these images in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you won't do that, but do you dig down, believe that everything worked out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, but fine, you have that belief, no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you do in account with?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you, like, put that belief first, and then all the effort, the renunciation, reflection, giving up that you have to do, that you know you have to do if you want to practice dhamma?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Try your best and, you know, but deep down believe that everything will work out, although you are not really putting the effort first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you really putting the effort first and disregarding the belief?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's there or not doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is whether you make the effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that always comes back to that simile of the the chicken with its eggs.
[SPEAKER_00]: If a chicken, even if she wishes, every minute of her life, may these chicks, my chicks, pierce safely from these shells,
[SPEAKER_00]: But she doesn't sit on the eggs long enough, well enough, often enough, they won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you have the other chick, whether even she doesn't wish for the chicken.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether she doesn't wish for the chicks to pierce out, they will, because she is doing the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's always like...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you putting the work first?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you believe that everything will work out and you're doing your best?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you putting that first?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because otherwise, it's a bit too much pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you do... are you doing the Jain prasada?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, these are like the obvious kind of clean-cut examples, but you could... if you discern the principle, you could see how it would apply to many of the contemporary things that are... that are done and placed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Purification through mantra, purification through incense, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through... through techniques, through methods, purification through
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I won't have to think, sustain, ponder on danger, and develop the context, and reflect, and get the right view first.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just do this exercise, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just watch my nostrils like this, walk like this, attend to this, feel like this, and then I'll be purified.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's like, the only way for purification to occur is if you already can and have seen the signs of your mind, the phenomenon, the cittanimitta, for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you basically have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without the right view, the domain where purification happens, is just invisible to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why often, without the right view, any such practice does kind of imply, to some degree, you know, when everybody starts the practice, you're new to it, you get your ideas, and the idea of enlightenment, insight, sotāpatti, it always has almost like this, requires this magical leap.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I'm doing all this stuff, I'm committed, I'm doing these practices, and then,
[SPEAKER_00]: The right view will happen to me, or arahantship will happen to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you don't really see where purification is and where it happens, because that's where it happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you purify it, that's what the right view is, when the mind is purified enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to purify it enough, you can't just wish for it to happen on account of these observances you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only if you see it where it needs to be purified, what it needs to be purified.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you start seeing what the mind is,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, as the sutta says, cittanimitta is the prerequisite for the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you know exactly what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there is no more magical leaps involved, or doing this for this to happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesome intention, unwholesome intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cultivating one's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Dirt and cleanliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dirt and cleanliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see exactly what needs to be cleaned, and how, and to what extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you can start the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's at least when you know what the work is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you see it clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all, you know, you reason, you measure the task.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see what it needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it's easy to do it, because now you see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it's all like sort of, you know, at arm's length, with certain kind of magical leaps in connection, just hoping for it to happen, then
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's on the level of wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, whatever happens, you don't even know if it's good or bad, important or unimportant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're already bent on it being the right thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's when people start interpreting any mundane stuff as spiritual stuff, because of the context of their spiritual practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if they didn't have the context of the spiritual practice that they developed, their inspiration, you would just see it as just the mundane stuff, which is some new experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Novelty this, novelty that, there's nothing to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, there's much more to it, because of my already pre-decided belief that there will be a lot more to it, because I'm practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that does go hand in hand with that view that everything will work out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever I'm doing, on account of my inspiration to practice dhamma, doesn't matter whether I see it, whether it's directly related, how it's related, whether it's bringing our wholesome to increase,
[SPEAKER_00]: Wholesome to decrease or wholesome to increase, unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if I see that clearly, if I fully understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if I see the saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if I have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do have the pure, wholesome intention to practice the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, whatever I do on account of that, it's towards the goal of nibbāna and the dhamma, and I'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a very dangerous view to have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as we said in previous talks,
[SPEAKER_00]: In the suttas, one of the definitions of the right view is knowing important as important and unimportant as unimportant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without knowing that, people end up doing unimportant as important and overlooking the important.
[SPEAKER_00]: And often people do overlook, like... See, the Buddha describes exactly how to calm your mind, how to experience joy, how to purify your mind, if you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think these themes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sustain them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Observe them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Make an observance out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: For many people, that's exactly as you said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, that's just thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not as important.
[SPEAKER_00]: See?
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude for somebody who would say, well, that's just merely thinking about the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not as important.
[SPEAKER_00]: There must be something more important.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You overlooked what's actually important.
[SPEAKER_00]: And went further and you lost it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that is what's important.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do it long enough, you'll see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but that's just thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just contemplation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anybody can do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but how many people actually do it like that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How many people do it on the basis of the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: But exactly, whoever reads that, many people would read that, and you almost don't even read it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just, oh yeah, Buddha, Dhamma, Saṅgha, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: I approve of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you observe it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you make a theme to ponder on these qualities?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you dig them up?
[SPEAKER_00]: Revisit them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Establish your mind
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, develop inspiration towards those... Not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say inspiration, I don't mean uplifting of faith where everything will work out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm inspired.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inspiration to think more about you what you already been thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: To really get even more clarity in regard to... to what needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, if you think that it's... Oh, that's just that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's self-evident.
[SPEAKER_00]: You overlooked the important.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see this not so important.
[SPEAKER_00]: I...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unimportant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's go through the second.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is the case where a disciple, a noble disciple, recollects the dhamma also, you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... or recollects the saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, you see, like recollects the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does not mean you recollect...
[SPEAKER_00]: I recollect the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: The dhamma is the great.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollects any aspect, practical aspect of the Buddhist enlightenment, the teacher, what he teaches.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recollect the dhamma through recollecting any relevant context, theme, on account of which you kind of have the right view already, that can now further it even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, dhamma is the great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma is the greatest teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, don't recollect it in a personal, kind of glorifying sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollect it in the same sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollecting the quality of the Buddha, the teacher, it's well-expounded, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: it's worth committing to, personally,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's worth for me to commit to the teaching of this teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, there is some faith involved, but only so that you can do it and start seeing it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about worshipping the saṅgha?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not about worshipping the Buddha either, nor the saṅgha, nor the dhamma, the teaching, the great tipiṭaka.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's bow to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Involving yourself personally with it, so that you can start doing it, so that you can become free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, all of these recollections don't require you to meet the Buddha, nor the saṅgha for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, the teaching, freedom from suffering,
[SPEAKER_00]: Having obviously understood enough, initially, where the problem is, where the mind is, develop the right view, now recollect the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollect the quality of the Buddha, the teacher, how what he said you should do and practice and develop, it's worth, because you can see it for yourself already, the benefits and the results of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just keep reminding yourself of that, sustain that as a context, then your mind will... well, will become unable to... to be defiled.
[SPEAKER_01]: And something I left out was, when recollecting the dhamma, the samādhi is like cleaning your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recollecting the Buddha is cleaning your head.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a good practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And recollecting the samādhi would be cleaning your clothes, putting on new clothes, fresh clothes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all about cleansing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a case where the noble disciple recollects his own virtues, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, my virtues are unbroken, unspotted, unsplattered, untarnished, liberating, praised by the wise, conducive to samādhi, to composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: As he's recollecting his virtue, his mind is calm, joy arises, the defilements of his mind are abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as when a mirror is cleansed through proper technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now the example is cleaning a mirror.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, that's the technique.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recollection, context on the basis of factual sense restraint and not giving in to unwholesome behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keeping the virtue unbroken, recollecting it, gladness, joy, samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is what samādhi is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Established context of the right kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the technique?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the technique of cleaning the mirror, the mechanical technique of cleaning the mirror.
[SPEAKER_00]: Except, you realize up there is nothing mechanical can be done about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you start mechanically recollecting the virtue, the dhamma, the saṅgha... You won't last long.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't last.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why all people need something more palpable.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, but tell me what to do, you know, with my body, with my attention, with my sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell me something more palpable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it must recollect my own virtues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, that would also be the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Do I keep five precepts?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eight precepts, five precepts, eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is the result of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the result of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Uplifting... Where are my values?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you start realizing where your values are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it on the value of the shepherd?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, I want this, I do it, I want that, now I do this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it on the value... No, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: This observance of the precepts, it needs to be undertaken, like, infinitely, for the rest of my life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I said that before, you know, it's better to take the five precepts for the rest of your life, than eight precepts on the weekend.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you will feel the weight of it, the context of it, and that's already a better basis for... then you can take eight within that, and so on, but you will never go below five.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're just taking occasionally, picking and choosing, your spiritual practice becomes like the shepherd's desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want this,
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now I have too much of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now I want a spiritual practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Up until I forget, then I want back to this, then to this, and it's just flopping from one to the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a case where a noble disciple recollects the devas.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, there are these devas in these heavens, these great kings and so on, who have the power over others' creations.
[SPEAKER_01]: He thinks about all these other heavens, heavenly realms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Conviction, I think it means faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever factors, whatever generosity they had, whatever discernment they had, all those things are present within me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why those beings went to heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you can... you can feel confident that the worst-case scenario, if you don't take your right view further, you'll at least be in the heavens.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the worst-case scenario, which is not a bad scenario, from the human point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm still going to a good place.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm still headed in the right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you say, well, but I don't, you know, I don't see the devas and the kings and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have faith in the Buddha, on account of which you practiced and developed the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you see for yourself freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see for yourself the benefit of faith, virtue, discernment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, the same source, the Buddha, who taught you these things that are kind of impossible to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize the depth of the dhamma when you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize how it's... how it cannot be obtained by accident.
[SPEAKER_00]: How it is truly a miracle that sort of, you know, the self-awakened one discovered and taught to others.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, he says these other things about rewards in heavens that I don't necessarily see, but I have absolutely no basis to doubt it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what, you know, what pertains to the core of the holy life has been understood,
[SPEAKER_00]: And he came from the same source that also says, and see, if you don't get anywhere, at least you'll be in heaven.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because Sariputta, the second after the Buddha, in terms of this sermon, couldn't see the heaven or understand the devas or anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had faith in them, they were real, because obviously the Buddha said so, but he couldn't see any of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the point of that sutta where he heard somebody ask him about, he heard that, oh, there's these devas that live
[SPEAKER_00]: Many of them live on the single-placed... No, space on a needle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they don't feel crowded and confined with each other, because their minds are so lofty and developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And Sariputra thought what to make of it, and he says, oh, it's because they practiced... they developed their minds over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was his answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, on the basis of reasoning here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't see the devas.
[SPEAKER_00]: He couldn't see how and why.
[SPEAKER_00]: He couldn't talk to them, as some other monks could.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the devas heard that and told the Buddha to tell him that he was wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, it was their minds developed during the human life.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, they're enjoying benefits.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the Buddha told that to Sariputta.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was like, oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he couldn't see it for himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be the extension of the faith, but it's also, again, just to calm your mind down.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there's pressure, disturbances, but you do have the right view, but you might be overwhelmed, nevertheless, illness, something's happening, whatever else, hardships, bearing too much of the elements is just adding up, reflect on these things and you get samādhi as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, it did come from the same source.
[SPEAKER_00]: The source that taught you the right view, and not to suffer amid suffering,
[SPEAKER_00]: We also talked about these other rewards, that why would he have a reason to lie, if he already showed you something that no other teaching shows you, that doesn't require anything from you, doesn't require worship, doesn't require some weird kind of sacrificial, just requires good virtue, which is good regardless of the religion, not killing, not stealing, not cheating, not lying.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's good regardless of what your views are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensory strength, not engaging in sensuality, that's verifiable here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's burden, it's unpleasant, it's peril, it results in more, more weight.
[SPEAKER_00]: All things you can see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's freed me from all those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's always like one of the first... come and see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people ask you what you're teaching, come and see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't... By all means, I urge you to not take it merely on faith and inspiration and how radiant I look or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, the Buddha said to come and see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The last bit is, furthermore, the disciple of the noble ones, noble disciple, reflects thus, as long as they live, the arahants abandon the taking of life, abstain from the taking of life, dwell with their weapons laid down, so on, compassionate for the welfare of all living beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today, I too, for this day and night, abandoning the taking of life,
[SPEAKER_01]: compassionate for the welfare of all living beings by by means of this factor i emulate the arahants and my poster will be observed so by so a noble disciple he takes on this thing and says i just do it for this day and night
[SPEAKER_01]: And so on with, take, you know, not stealing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as they live, the arahants abandon un-celibacy, the sexuality, the sexual act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Live a celibate life, secluded, refrain from the sexual act that is the village's way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Today I too, for this day and night, abandon un-celibacy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the difference between somebody just claiming to do that for a day and night,
[SPEAKER_00]: And Noble Disciple is doing it for a day and night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, it implies Noble Disciple will go back to his life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, would become un-celibate and so on, if he doesn't want to practice further.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, he is truthful during that day and night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is he truthful and the previous example wasn't truthful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is he... Well, he's... What is he doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, the first guy with giant observances also doesn't kill a dozen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, he's not truthful from the start.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no disciple is truthful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the difference?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they both decide from the start they're only going to do it for 24 hours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But one is truthful, the other one isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he understands.
[SPEAKER_00]: What?
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands what?
[SPEAKER_01]: He understands what he's doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: He understands that he's cleansing the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not doing it out of wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows that he is cleansing the mind in this way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he has direct insight into the behavior of an Arahant, into the mind of an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what Sotapatta is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding what Arahantship is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, tailoring and shaping your life, your decisions, your intentions, to fully support
[SPEAKER_00]: The understanding of arahant's mind is what nibbāna will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will result in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when a noble disciple then says, I shall emulate the virtue, the behavior of an arahant, he understands exactly what that is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for that 24 hours, he is actually doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although he knows he won't sustain it,
[SPEAKER_00]: At least his recognition of what he's doing pertains directly to what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like I just take on this method, this behavior, this technique, this observance for the wishful thinking of being an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I don't see for myself what arahant is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Noble disciple does.
[SPEAKER_01]: He takes that practice up.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can pick it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's the only one that can.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it remains perpetually available.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not engage with it all the time, as there were cases of careless sotāpānas in the suttas, lay people, you know, drinking and doing this and that, but the view that they can perpetually turn to and take on, the view of arahantship, that then they can commit to it, they choose, if the sense of urgency sort of prods them in their direction, that remains, because that's what sotāpāna is, having that view accessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The view of where the mind is and what the right practice is, what the right taming is, exactly what escape is.